How did you get on with
the assignment three?
I kept it short since I wanted to give
you a lot of time to come to terms with
the tricky notion of implication.
This lecture's going to
be fairly short as well,
though the assignment that goes with it
will be the longest of the entire course.
I'm not expecting you to complete
it all by the next lecture, though.
The next topic I want to look
at is logical equivalence.
Equivalence is closely
related to implication.
Two statements are said to be equivalent,
or
more fully, logically equivalent,
if each implies the other.
Equivalence is a central
notion in mathematics.
Many mathematical results are proofs
that two statements are equivalent.
In fact, equivalence is to logic as
equations are to arithmetic and algebra.
And you already know that equations
play a central role in mathematics.
Just as we had to introduce
a formal version of implication
that avoids the complex issue of
causation, namely the conditional,
we have to introduce an analogous
version of equivalence.
It's called the biconditional.
Fortunately, we did all
the difficult work with implication.
Now we can reap the benefits
of those efforts.
Two statements phi and psi are said
to be logically equivalent, or
just equivalent,
if each implies the other.
Since we have a formal
version of implication,
named the conditional, it follows that
there's a formal version of equivalence.
We call it the biconditional.
The biconditional of phi and
psi is denoted by means of
a double-headed arrow, like this.
Formally, the biconditional is
an abbreviation of phi conditional psi and
psi conditional phi.
Since the conditional is defined
in terms of truth values,
it follows that the biconditional is
defined in terms of truth values.
If you work out the truth table for
phi conditional psi and for
psi conditional phi and
then you work out the conjunction,
you'll get the truth table for
phi biconditional psi.
And if you do that, what you will find
is that phi biconditional psi is true,
if phi and psi are both true or
if they're both false.
One way to show that two statement phi and
psi are equivalent is to show
they have the same truth tables.
Actually, to avoid confusion,
let me change those to capital Phi and
capital Psi, because I want to use the
lower case phi and psi for something else.
Because here's the example
that I'm going to look at.
I want to show that phi
conjoined with psi or not phi-
Is equivalent- To phi conditional psi.
This is actually going to
be my capital Phi, and
this is going to be my capital Psi.
If I was teaching this material
at a high school level,
I'd be very careful to choose different
letters to denote everything but
we're looking at college,
university level mathematics now.
And university mathematicians,
professional mathematicians
frequently use upper and
lower case symbols in the same context.
And part of being able to master
university level mathematics is actually
getting use to disambiguous notations.
What we have to do is work up the truth
table for this, the truth table for that,
and show that they're the same.
We'll start with phi, psi, and we're
going to need to work out phi and psi.
We're going to need to work out not phi.
Then I'm going to need to work out phi and
psi disjoined with not phi, and
then I'm going to have to compare
that with phi conditional psi.
As usual, we start with
the four combinations, TT, TF,
FT, FF.
By the way, it doesn't matter
which order you right these in, so
long as you get all four
possible combinations.
The way I've written it is the way
that most mathematicians write it.
Conjunction.
Conjunction is true if
the two conjuncts are true.
TT gives T, here there's an F,
so you're going to get an F.
Here there's an F, so
you're going to get an F.
We have two Fs, so
Negation simply flips T and F, so
we have T T F F becomes F F T T.
Now I'm going to disjoin this with that,
and disjunction picks out at least one T.
There's a T there, so
I'm going to get a T here.
There's no T, so I'm going to get an F.
There's a T there, which gives me a T, and
there's a T there, which gives me a T.
I know the truth value is for
Phi conditional Psi.
They were T, F, T, T.
If you look back at the earlier work,
you'll see that that's what
we worked out before and
now I just compare that
column with that column.
T F T T is the same T F T T.
Because these two columns are the same,
I can conclude
that is equivalent to that.
I should mention that proving equivalence
by means of truth tables is very unusual.
It's only of a special
case of equivalence.
In general,
proving equivalence is really quite hard.
You have to look at what
the two statements mean and
develop a proof based on their meaning.
Equivalence itself is not too
difficult a notion to deal with.
What is problematic is mastering
the various nomenclatures
that are associated with implication.
We start out with the notion,
phi implies psi.
I'm really going to be thinking
of genuine implication here, but
you can interpret everything else
in terms of the conditional.
We'll look at that,
I'll talk about that a little bit later.
If mathematicians always describe
this situation in this way,
then life would be very simple.
But we don't.
There are many different expressions
we use to describe phi implies psi.
Some them are intuitively obvious and
some of them
are actually counter-intuitive
when you first meet them.
The following all mean phi implies psi.
One, if phi, then psi.
Okay, that's fairly obvious.
Two, phi is sufficient for psi.
In order to conclude that psi,
it suffices to know phi.
On the face of it, that's fairly
straightforward but in complicated
situations, people can sometimes get
misled by the use of the word sufficient.
The use of the word sufficient is by no
means the most problematic In
the context of implication.
This one causes people
a lot of problems at first.
Phi only if psi.
That's not the same as if psi then phi.
The reason I'm emphasizing that is
that the if here goes with the psi.
Just as it does here.
Let's put quotes on that one.
The if goes with the psi,
the if goes with the psi.
But when it's expressed in
this way with an only if,
it flips around the order
of the implication.
For example, some of you may know
that I'm a very keen cyclist.
On the other hand, I've never qualified,
nor have I ridden in the Tour de France.
However, I could honestly say a person
could ride in the Tour de France
only if they have a bicycle.
Well, that's true because if you
don't have a bicycle you can't
ride in the Tour de France.
So a person can ride in the Tour de
France only if they have a bicycle.
Now that's true for me.
But it doesn't mean the same
as if you have a bicycle
then you can ride in the Tour de France.
I actually do have a bicycle,
I have several, but
I can't ride in the Tour de France.
So it's true to say, Keith could ride
in the Tour de France only if he
had a bicycle,
because that's true for everybody.
You can only ride in the Tour
de France if you have a bicycle.
Otherwise you can't ride in it.
But it's not the same as
saying it this way around.
That if you have a bicycle,
then you can ride in the Tour de France.
So, gotta be a little bit careful.
These are often confused which is
why I'm stressing the distinction.
Okay?
Let's look at this one because this one,
that I'm going to write next, is one that
I've already really encountered in my
discussions about the Tour de France.
Psi if phi,
notice that we've flipped the order now.
Phi is the antecedent,
psi is the consequent.
Let me write those down,
just to remind us.
Phi is the antecedent.
And psi is a consequent.
And those are the roles going to be
played by phi and psi in all of these.
So phi is the antecedent,
psi is the consequent.
Phi is the antecedent,
Phi is the antecedent.
Psi is the consequence.
They've flipped.
Phi is still the antecedent.
Psi is still the consequence.
This still means that Phi implies Psi.
But now the consequent comes first.
The antecedent comes second.
Psi if phi.
If like me you're a cyclist, you can think
about that in terms of owning a bike and
riding in the Tour de France or
use your own favorite example.
Think of something that you
do that requires something,
that requires some equipment or
some preparation or something.
And just interpret these things in
terms of something that's meaningful in
your life.
Now that should help
you to sort these out.
Okay, there's a couple
more I want to talk about.
Psi Whenever phi.
Again, the order is flipped
from the order in implication.
That's still the consequence.
That's the antecedent, but they've
been written the opposite way around,
psi whenever phi.
And finally, psi is
necessary for phi.
Again, the order is flipped around.
That's still the consequent,
that's still the antecedent.
Psi is necessary for phi.
In order to ride in the Tour de France
it's necessary that you have a bicycle.
It's not sufficient that
you have a bicycle.
To ride in the Tour de France it's
necessary that you have a bicycle but
it's not sufficient that
you have a bicycle.
That's the example that I would use for
all of these but
you can pick your own favorite
example to understand these things.
It's important to really
master this terminology
because it's used all the time, not
just in mathematics, but in science and
in analytic reasoning and
thought in general.
This is not just mathematical language,
this is the language that people use in
legal documents, in logical arguments,
in analytic arguments, and
in discussions and so forth.
So understanding language as it's used
is very important in many walks of life.
And having introduced terminology
commonly associated with implication.
We have an associated terminology for
equivalence.
Phi is equivalent to psi
is itself equivalent to,
by the way this already shows how
ubiquitous the equivalence is because
the obvious word to describe this, let me
put quotes around that just to ambiguate.
The obvious way to describe that
this is equivalent to something
is to use the word equivalence as well.
I mean, equivalence is just a very
basic concept in mathematics.
So this sentence, this statement,
this claim is itself equivalent to,
well, phi is necessary and
sufficient for psi.
This combination of necessary and
sufficient is very common in mathematics.
And b, phi, If and only if psi.
That's also very common in mathematics,
if and only if.
Notice that we combining necessary and
sufficient.
With necessary we have psi before phi.
With sufficient we have phi before psi and
that get's us the implication
in both directions, and equivalence
means implication in both directions.
So, the fact that it's in both directions
is captured by the fact that here we have
the psi before the phi, and
here we have the phi before the psi.
Similarly with b.
If and only if combines only if,
where phi comes before psi, with if,
where psi comes before phi.
So in both of these cases we have
an implication from phi to psi and
from psi to phi.
Final remark.
This expression is often abbreviated,
iff.
Iff is a standard
mathematician's abbreviation.
For if and only if.
So, if and only if or
if if means the two things are equivalent.
Okay.
Once you've mastered this terminology you
should be able to read and
make sense of Pretty well any
mathematics that you come across.
That doesn't mean to say you
understand the mathematics itself, but
at least you should be able to
understand what it's talking about.
And that's a first step towards
understanding the mathematics itself.
And that's all there is to say about this.
The rest is really up to you to spend
some time mastering the concepts and
the associated terminology.
Time for a quiz.
This quiz comes in four parts.
So how did you do?
Well, let's see what's going on here.
Which of the following
conditions is necessary for
the natural number n to
be a multiple of 10?
So the question we have
to ask ourselves is.
Does n being a multiple of 10
Imply the statement.
To be necessary, n being a multiple
of 10 has to imply the statement.
Well let's see.
Does n being a multiple of 10
imply that it's a multiple of 5?
Yes it does, so that one's necessary.
Does n being a multiple of 10
imply this is a multiple of 20?
10 is itself a multiple of 10.
But 10 is certainly not a multiple of 20.
Does n being multiple of 10 imply that n
is even and that it's a multiple of 5?
Yes, does n being a multiple of 10
imply that it's a multiple of 100?
No, does n being a multiple of 10 imply
that n squared is a multiple of 100?
Yes, so the three conditions
that are necessary for
the number n to be a multiple of 10.
Condition one, condition three,
condition five.
Okay, let's move on to Part 2.
Well this time,
we have to ask the question,
does the statement imply
n is a multiple of 10.
Okay well, does this statement
imply that n is a multiple of 10?
No it doesn't.
5 is itself a multiple of 5.
5 is not a multiple of 10.
Look at number two,
is it the case that if n is a multiple of
20 then it has to be a multiple of 10?
Does this imply that?
The answer is yes.
Does n being even and a multiple of
5 imply that it's a multiple 10?
Yes.
If n is 100, does that imply
that it's a multiple of 10?
Yes, if n squared is a multiple of 100,
does that imply that
it's a multiple of 10?
Yes, so in this case, 2, 3, 4,
and 5 are the correct answers.
They're all sufficient for
n being a multiple of 10.
Okay, let's move on to part three.
For this one, we have to compare our
answers for the two previous questions.
The first question was necessity and
the second question is sufficiency.
For necessity, we had 1,
we had 3, and we had 5.
For sufficiency we had 2, 3, 4, and 5.
This asks for necessity and sufficiency.
Here we've just got necessity, there we've
just sufficiency,
there we have both of them.
There we just have sufficiency,
So the one's that are necessary and
sufficient, this one and that one.
Okay, let's move on to part four.
For this one, the question we have to ask
ourselves is, what does the implying?
Well, in number one,
this does the implying.
So that's the antecedent.
In question two of statement two.
Well, even though it's written
the opposite way around,
it's essentially the same statement.
It's the alarm ringing
that does the implying.
What about number three?
Keith cycles only if the sun shines,
what's doing the implying?
Keith cycling, if you see me cycling,
you can conclude that the Sun's shining
because I cycle only if the sun shines.
Incidentally, I was brought up in England,
so that's not the case.
I'm quite happy to, well,
I'm not happy to ride in the rain, but
I do ride in the rain.
But it's a good example.
Number four, what does the implying?
Well, Amy arrives does the implying.
So far, I've distinguished
between genuine implication and
equivalents, and
they're far more counterparts.
The conditional and the bi-conditional.
In the daily work however,
Mathematicians are very not particular.
For instance, we often use the arrow
symbol as an abbreviation for implies.
On the double headed arrow is
an abbreviation for is equivalent to.
Although this is a very confusing
to beginners, it's simply the way
a mathematical practice is evolved and
there's no getting around it.
In fact, once you get used to the notions,
it's not all this confusing as it
might seem at first and here is why.
The conditional and bi-conditional only
differ from implication and equivalents
in situations that do not adrise in
the cause of normal mathematical practice.
In any real mathematical context, the
conditional effectively is implication,
and the bi-conditional
effectively is equivalent.
So having made note of where the formal
notions differ from the everyday ones,
mathematicians simply move on and
turn their attention to other things.
The very act of formulating formal
definitions creates an understanding
of implication and equivalence that allows
us to use the everyday notion safely.
Of course, computer programmers and
people who develop aircraft control
systems don't have such freedom.
They have to make sure all the notions
in their programs are defined and
give answers in all circumstances.
Okay, that's the end of lecture four.
As I said at the start,
it's been a fairly short lecture.
My reason for keeping the lecture short is
that the upcoming assignment is much
longer than the others, it has to be.
Implication and equivalence
are at the heart of mathematics.
Mastery of those concepts and
of the terminology associated with them
is fundamental to mathematical thinking.
You simply have to master implication and
equivalents before you
can go much further.
And there's only one way
to achieve mastery, right?
Remember the story of the elderly lady who
approached a New York City policeman and
asked, officer,
how do I get to Carnegie Hall?
The officer smiled and said, lady,
there's only one way,
practice, practice, practice.
So, I suggest you carve out some time,
grab some food and drink, and head off
somewhere quiet to complete as much of
assignment four as you possibly can.